Guide to the A Gathering of the Tribes Records MSS.198
Fales Library and Special Collections
A Gathering of the Tribes Records
1976-2019
Fales Library and Special Collections
Gathering of the Tribes (Gallery)
Cannon, Steve, 1935-2019
MSS.198
30 Linear Feet in 9 record cartons, 25 manuscript boxes, 7 binders, 1 small flat box, 2 oversize flat boxes, 1 flat-file folder, 4 audiocassettes in a shared box, 1 file in a shared tall LP box, 18 born-digital carriers in two shared boxes, and 8 containers with unknown profiles.
20.48 Gigabytes in 335 computer files
305 items on audio and video carriers.
Founded in 1991 in writer Steve Cannon's home, A Gathering of the Tribes was conceived as a venue in New York's East Village for underexposed artists, a networking center, and a place for the development of new talent through its gallery, performance space, and publishing company. The A Gathering of the Tribes Records contain material documenting the administration and wide array of activities of this organization including event promotional material; press clippings; scrapbooks; photographs and albums; audio and video recordings; and financial and administrative files. The collection also includes artist submissions and exhibition files for the Tribes Gallery, as well as writer submissions and project files for both Fly By Night Press and the magazine A Gathering of the Tribes. Ephemera and writings by A Gathering of the Tribes founder Steve Cannon are also in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The A Gathering of the Tribes Records were purchased by NYU's Fales Library and Special Collections from Steve Cannon in 2007. An accretion of materials was transferred in May 2021; the accession numbers associated with these accessions are 2007.198 and 2021.013, respectively.
Appraisal
In November 2021, audiovisual recordings containing off-air content with mold contamination were deaccessioned. In September 2023, the following were removed from the collection: (3) 3.5 Floppy Disks, (1) zip drive, and (30) CDs (due to damage or duplicates); an orginal artwork; and 13 books and publications that already existed in the collection.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into seven series, with Series I. dividing further into two subseries.
Series I. Audiovisual Recordings
Subseries I.A. Video
Subseries I.B. Audio
Series II. Photograph Albums and Scrapbooks
Series III. Project Files
Series IV. Grant Files
Series V. Financial Records
Series VI. Publications
Series VII. Steve Cannon Papers
Historical Note
A Gathering of the Tribes was a performance space, art gallery, literary magazine, and small print publisher in New York's East Village. Founded in 1991 by Steve Cannon in his brownstone apartment building, Tribes began as an informal salon for cultural exchange between poets, artists, musicians and performers. The collaborative, explorative work done in the space culminated in the founding of the A Gathering of the Tribes magazine, whose first issue was published in the autumn of 1991. Since its inception, A Gathering of the Tribes sought to engage with and promote work from multi-cultural, interdisciplinary, and underrepresented writers and artists. A Gathering of the Tribes was a contributor to the East Village literary, artistic and performance scene alongside such venues as Nuyorican Poets Cafe and the Living Theatre. In 1993, a portion of the space became the Tribes Gallery, hosting exhibitions, readings, and performances. In April of 2014 both the organization and Steve Cannon were forced to relocate and the gallery permanently closed when the occupancy agreement with the person to whom the building had previously been sold ended. Fly By Night Press stopped publishing in 2018, but Tribes magazine continutes to publishing online. Steve Cannon passed away in 2019.
Source:
"About." A Gathering of the Tribes. Web. 22 September 2023. https://www.tribes.org/our-story
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to select audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Some audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Scope and Contents
The A Gathering of the Tribes Records (1983-2012) documents the operations and programs of A Gathering of the Tribes, which served as a neighborhood arts center through its gallery, performance space, as well as a literary magazine and book publisher for artists, writers, and performers. This collection contains paper, computer files, and audiovisual recordings generated by A Gathering of the Tribes while the organization served as a gathering space for lesser-known, local New York City artists and writers during the 1990s to the 2010, providing a space to form networks and host events supporting the arts in the East Village. This collection includes video and audio recordings, publicity material, guest books, and scrapbooks documenting the organization's performances, readings, and gallery openings. Project files typically contain correspondence; Fly By Night Press manuscript submissions; artist submissions for the gallery; and business and administrative records. Grant files chronicle A Gathering of the Tribes' pursuit of funding through extensive individual source files, providing insight into the financial struggles of a small New York arts organization through applications, rejection letters, correspondence, and final reports. A small selection of ephemera and writings by Tribes founder Steve Cannon include essays, plays, and short stories, some of which were co-written, while others were produced with the assistance of a transcriber due to Cannon's visually-impaired status. The publications series contains printed material published by Fly By Night Press, or in some way associated with A Gathering of the Tribes.
Separated Materials
Four issues of A Gathering of the Tribes were removed from the archive to be catalogued. They can be found in the Fales Library's Downtown Collection, via Bobcat.
Grant proposals.; East Village (New York, N.Y.); Scrapbooks.; Magazines (Periodicals); Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York -- 20th century.; Videocassettes.; Video recordings.; Poetry slams.; Spoken word poetry; Photographs.; Grants.; Artists and community -- New York (State) -- New York; Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fliers (printed matter); Photograph albums.; Cannon, Steve, 1935-2019; Kim, Anyssa; Fly By Night Press
- Series I. Audiovisual Recordings, 1983-2011; 13 Linear Feet in 9 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, 1 unknown profile containers, and 4 items in a shared cassette box.; 18.99 Gigabytes in 11 computer files; 305 items on audio and video carriers.
  Arrangement
  This series is divided into two subseries and are arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains audiovisual materials dating from 1983 to 2011 for A Gathering of the Tribes. Recordings contain audio and video footage of poetry readings, performance art pieces, gallery openings, and musical performances that took place at Steve Cannon's East Village home which was the location for A Gathering of the Tribes.
  - Subseries I.A. Video, 1983-2011
    This subseries is arranged in chronological order, with commercial recordings listed at the end of the inventory in alphabetical order.
    This subseries contains video recordings of A Gathering of the Tribes events and performances as well as early recordings from other related events in New York. This subseries also contains commercial recordings of movies and television shows, more than likely for personal consumption by Tribes staff or founder Steve Cannon.
    - Alice Zinnes: Tribes Production, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0017, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0017)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 3 min.
    - Allan Mazzini; Keychwa's Current Event Scratch, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements; Label annotations: "Crank up the volume, please!"; "Please Excuse Sound Quality! It gets better as it moves on". (Box 6, Cassette ID: 198.0225, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0225)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 12 min.
    - Amy Ouzoonian & Inez, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0137, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0137)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 61 min.
    - Big Guns / Bette Davis Interview / Bombshell (Harlow), circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0261)
      Existence and Location of Copies
      Currently no access copy is available.
    - "Blight Spirit," Steve Cannon, Ishmael Cannon, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0130, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0130)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 48 min.
    - Bravo - Sugartown 8-10 / [Hamptons], circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 9, Cassette ID: 198.0301)
    - CBS / [M..] / M. Mono, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0262)
      Original Format: VHS
    - Ceci N'est Pas Un Peepshow, Cuns Interactabilis i.e., circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0259, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0259)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 16 min.
    - Butch Morris - Poets Choir at Whitney / Steve Cannon's Top of the World at Context, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0094, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0094)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 126 min.
    - Canada Trust TVC, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0003, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0003)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 10 min.
      Cantonese commercials.
    - Charlie Parker: Veritas Documentary, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0149, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0149)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 29 min.
    - Cheryl B Taylor - Tribes Open Mike, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 2, Cassette ID: 198.0038, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0038)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 57 min.
    - Choreography Johons [Analhous], circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 8, Cassette ID: 198.0272, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0272)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 68 min.
    - (Class [...]), circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0297)
    - Closing Party (Poetry Reading) for Long Shot Magazine, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 9, Cassette ID: 198.0319, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0319)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 82 min.
    - Coltrane / Jumeel Moon Doc and Dancers / October Blight, / Eleventh and B., circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Label annotations: "Video Void (Timing?)" (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0020, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0020)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 240 min.
    - Daniel Pollack, Writer/Director, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: 00:08:00; Promotional "highlight reel" video.; Original Format: VHS (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0231)
    - Do the Right Thing, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: approx. 02:00:00; Original Format: VHS (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0119)
    - Dominique Lowell: Women are Hungry, Sugar Daddy, When the Bitch Puts on Aretha You Know Theres Trouble (in 3 Parts), circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0084, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0084)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 13 min., Preservation Note: There was a video effect used at the start of the source tape.
    - Edwin Torres / Sharon Mesner / Open Mike, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Label annotation: "Sunday, April" (Box 2, Cassette ID: 198.0049, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0049)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 72 min.
    - Emile de Antonio: Painters Painting, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Commercial Release (Mystic Fire Video).; Original Format: VHS (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0104)
    - Fashion Show / Oops, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0228, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0228)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 24 min.
    - Four Women, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS. (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0234)
    - Friday June 16th, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 9, Cassette ID: 198.0311)
      DVD access copy available by appointment.
    - Gathering of the Tribes, Feb 15, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0174, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0174)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 55 min.
    - Groove, Bang & Jive Around, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0089, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0089)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 91 min.
    - Goussy's Birthday Party, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0167, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0167)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 60 min. Preservation Note: Audio in one channel only; picture is dark.
    - G.U.N. / Sex + Politics, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: approx. 00:24:20 (Box 6, Cassette ID: 198.0205, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0205)
      Separated Materials
      A postcard flyer for "Shade: Plays by Franco & Melanie Maria Goodreaux" was removed from the cassette sleeve and can be found in Series.
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 27 min.
    - Gunshot, by Individual Electric feat. Denis Giron; music: Central Park Drums & Los Papines, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: 00:05:38 (Box 6, Cassette ID: 198.0210, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0210)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 6 min.
    - Heaven & Hell - Return to Blowdryer!!, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 8, Cassette ID: 198.0264, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0264)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 40 min.
    - Hubba City, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Handwritten label on cassette case: "Fragile Tape - View with Caution." (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0025, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0025)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 103 min., Preservation Note: Picture quality is poor.
    - Interns, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 9, Cassette ID: 198.0308, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0308)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: Unknown
    - Ishmael Reed Interview, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0082, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0082)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 120 min.
    - Jalla! Jalla!, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 7, Cassette ID: 198.0235)
    - Jam Session at Tribes, Artist & Date unknown, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 8, Cassette ID: 198.0278, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0278)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 50 min.
    - John and 3 Women (Part) / Milo's Peach / FreeUSA Raw Footage, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0103, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0103)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 38 min.
    - John Farris / Eileen Myles, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0125, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0125)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 64 min.
    - K. Kurismaa, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0106)
      Original Format: VHS, Preservation note: The content appears to have been recorded in the PAL broadcast standard and has not been digitized.
    - Keats / GBS / Major Barbara, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0195)
    - The Last Poem, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS; Label annotation: "Directed by Darran Sampson." (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0019)
    - Lavinia Williams, Lecture Demonstration, St. Peter's Church, 1983; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0146, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0146)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 89 min.
    - Live from NYC GO Poetry, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements; Label annotation: "Date and Place unknown". (Box 8, Cassette ID: 198.0283, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0283)
    - Lorenzo Pace, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0131, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0131)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 34 min.
    - Machito - A Latin Jazz Legacy / Carlos Ortiz - Nubia Music Society, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0186)
    - Maria Sentis, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0026, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0026)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 60 min.
    - Medellin - N.Y.: Juan Raul Hoyos: Kikis Ups / Londorio: The Parabol of the Fisherman, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements (Box 6, Cassette ID: 198.0192, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0192)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 4 min.
    - Miguel's Reading, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0178, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0178)
    - Miles Davis - Unreleased!, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: approx. 01:18:00; Printed-out sleeve insert: "Miles Davis - West Germany 1967 & Berlin 1973", "Berlin - Philharmonie, 11/1/73", "Karlsruhe - Stadthalle, 11/7/67".; Original Format: VHS (Box 2, Cassette ID: 198.0051)
    - Nuyorican Poets Cafe: Short Poems / Poet's Choir "Butch Morris" / Slam - 6 Poets, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Label annotation: "Nick Video"; "Short Poems - 14 mins.; Poet's Choir 'Butch Morris' - 45 mins." (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0123, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0123)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 109 min.
    - My Fair Lady, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: 02:50:00; Original Format: VHS (Box 6, Cassette ID: 198.0194)
    - NASA Press Conference (Date Unknown), circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 52, Cassette ID: 198.0303)
    - New / Music / Miles, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0018, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0018)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 360 min.
      Content was recorded from television.
    - No Sucrose / Martha's "Mission of Love" at University of the Streets, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0096, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0096)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 95 min.
    - Ooh La La: Lina Pallotta, Steve Cannon, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0168, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0168)
    - The Poetry of Lester Afflick, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0006, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0006)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 30 min.
    - The Poetry of Lester Afflick, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Printed label: "Licensed for Private Viewing Only"; Original Format: VHS (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0072)
    - Poetry Reading - Melenie, Hershel, Steve Dalan, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0136, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0136)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 56 min., Preservation Note: Recorded in low light; very dark.
    - Poetry Reading: Michael Conroy Harris & Open Reading, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: 01:10:00 (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0169, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0169)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 70 min.
    - Police State, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0110, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0110)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 14 min.
    - Prince - Live in N.Y.C., circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: VHS (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0129)
    - Raw, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0179, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0179)
    - "Raw Fusion" Video Press Kit, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: 00:20:00 (Box 5, Cassette ID: 198.0182, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0182)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 18 min.
    - Sheila Alson Memorial, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 4, Cassette ID: 198.0138, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0138)
    - Star Black - Works on Papers @ the Tribes Gallery, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown (Box 1, Cassette ID: 198.0005, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0005)
    - Steve Cannon, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Original Format: DVD (Box 9, Disk ID: 198.0321)
    - Steve Cannon, Edwin Torres and DJ Spooky, circa 1983-2006; 1 media elements Total Running Time: Unknown; Sticker label on cassette: "Magneticfilms.net" (Box 3, Cassette ID: 198.0105, Box Digitized Access Files, File fales_mss198_0105)
      Original Format: VHS, Duration: 2 min.